Guide to the James Montgomery Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Letters from James Montgomery, 1789-1853; Series I; 129
  - Tilt and Bogue, of London, 1841 Jun 10 (Box 2, Folder 106)
    Autograph letter; this letter regards Mr. Comey's letter in The Gentleman's Magazine, respecting a new edition of Thomson's The Seasons.
  - Tipper and Fry, of London, 1813 Oct 25 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    Autograph letter, signed; Montgomery encloses £16 with this letter, to be placed to the credit of his account for stamps.
  - Westley and Davis, of London, 1830 Nov 18 (Box 2, Folder 108)
    Autograph letter, signed; regarding the "Missionary Journal" [ Journal of Voyages and Travels by Daniel Tyerman and George Bennet ] for which Montgomery has prepared the manuscript.
  - Wilkinson, Henry, of Endcliffe Hall, Sheffield, 1844 Jun 7 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    Autograph letter, signed; written from The Mount, Sheffield.
  - Williamson, James, of Leeds, 1824 Feb 7 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    Autograph letter; with regard to a monthly meeting held the previous evening.
  - Wood, J., of Manchester, 1840 Dec 8 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    Autograph letter; Montgomery thanks Mr. Wood for his invitation, but is unable to accept it.
  - Woodward, Sophia, of London, 1841 Jun 12 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Yates, James, of Sheffield, 1847 Sep 25 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Unidentified recipient, 1808 Sep 5 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    Montgomery mentions Latin, Latin poetry, and his school days.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1815 Dec 11 (Box 2, Folder 115)
    Autograph letter, signed; this letter deals with an account of Sheffield.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1817 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    Autograph letter, signed; written from Sheffield. Delivered by a Mrs. Megson to a certain lady, in respect to negotiations between her brother and James Montgomery.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1823 Jan 18 (Box 2, Folder 117)
    Autograph letter, signed; regarding his work, Polyhymnia, or Select Airs by Celebrated Foreign Composers. Montgomery requests that any copies remaining on hand are returned to him immediately.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1824 Feb 18 (Box 2, Folder 118)
    Autograph letter, signed; regarding certain papers which Montgomery states he returns, at the same time apologizing for having "kept them so long."
  - Unidentified recipient, 1824 Jul 23 (Box 2, Folder 119)
    Autograph letter, signed; dealing with some stanzas sent to Montgomery.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1828 Oct 21 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    Autograph letter, signed; Montgomery states that this arrived during his absence from home. He mentions the secretary of the Sheffield Literary and Philosophical Society, and also the Rev. Jack Hunter.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1831 Oct 24 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    Autograph letter, signed; Montgomery requests that 180 copies of his psalms and hymns are sent to Reverend Piccope in Manchester, and the order charged to the estate of Mrs. Cotterill.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1832 Dec 17 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    Autograph letter; regarding Mr. W. Saunders, a civil engineer. Montgomery, having known Mr. Saunders from his youth, and had business dealings with him, gives a good account of him.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1834 May 7 (Box 2, Folder 123)
    Autograph letter, signed; regarding the Missionary Festival at Wakefield. Written from Sheffield.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1838 Apr 20 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    Autograph letter, signed; this letter refers to a hymn composed by Montgomery for the Sunday School Union.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1841 Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    Autograph letter, signed; regarding a new edition of Montgomery's poems. He acknowledges receipt of twenty-five copies of same. Affixed to this letter is a newspaper clipping regarding Montgomery's pension.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1841 Jun 22 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    Autograph letter, signed; regarding a course of lectures which Montgomery has been asked to deliver.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1841 Dec 31 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    Autograph letter, signed; dealing with a meeting of the Board of Governors, at which Mr. J. Law was appointed House Surgeon. Montgomery returns the unsuccessful applicant's testimonials.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1851 Nov 4 (Box 2, Folder 128)
    Facsimile of letter written by Montgomery on his 80th birthday. This letter was given (with last page in facsimile) to Sheffield Weekly News, August 11, 1900.
  - Unidentified recipient, 1853 Feb 21 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    Autograph letter, signed; to his publishers requesting they send him copies of his hymns bound in purple morocco.
    Purchase, 1957.
- Writings of James Montgomery, 1821-1852; Series II; 26
  Arranged alphabetically by title of work, or first line of text.
  - "Abdallah a Sabat" and "The Grave", [1824] (Box 2, Folder 130)
    Poems translated into Welsh.
  - "Aspirations of Youth", 1841 Mar 11 (Box 2, Folder 131)
    Poem of five verses.
  - "The Christian Graces", 1842 Aug 23 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    Poem of four verses; 1 Corinthians XIII. 13.
  - "The Deaf Man's Soliloquy", undated (Box 2, Folder 133)
    Poem.
  - "The Dying Girl's Request", 1844 Sep 3 (Box 2, Folder 134)
    Poem of two verses. Written at Liverpool, and addressed to Miss M. A. M. Cottesworth, Liverpool.
  - "Epitaph on a Youth of 15 Years", 1847 Dec 23 (Box 2, Folder 135)
  - "Evening Time"; "Short Hand"; "The Gentianella"; "For Mrs. Hemans", 1828 Sep 28 (Box 2, Folder 136)
    Poems.
  - "For the Children of National or Sunday Schools", undated (Box 2, Folder 137)
    Poem. Five verses, accompanied by typed transcriptions.
  - "For the Red Hill Sunday School, 1827" (Box 2, Folder 138)
  - "In Affliction", 1852 Dec 29 (Box 2, Folder 139)
    Autograph poem; accompanied by an engraved portrait of Montgomery.
  - [A little Child who dare despise, These little ones of thine...], 1830 Jul 6 (Box 2, Folder 140)
  - [May the fair owner of this book, When days, and months, and years are fled...], 1843 Aug 17 (Box 2, Folder 141)
  - "A Missionary Lesson for Children", 1843 Aug 5 (Box 2, Folder 142)
    Poem in three parts, signed "J. M." and addressed to the Rev. William Bruce of Wadsley.
  - "A Motto for the Bible", 1840 May 14 (Box 2, Folder 143)
    Verse of four lines.
  - "Night", 1821 [Sep?] (Box 2, Folder 144)
  - "Night", 1833 Mar 16 (Box 2, Folder 145)
    Poem; not in Montgomery's hand.
  - [On earth we meet again below...], 1844 (Box 2, Folder 146)
    Poem of six verses.
  - "A Pilgrim's Retrospect," "For a Bride's Album," "To the Writers in This Book," "To the Reader," and "To Her Who Left This Book Behind", 1842 (Box 2, Folder 147)
  - "A Prayer for Every Day, and All Day Long", 1836 Jun 18 (Box 2, Folder 148)
  - "The Press", 1842 May (Box 2, Folder 149)
  - "Sandance's Dream", 1826 (Box 2, Folder 150)
    Essay telling of the dream of Sandance, a Negro youth.
  - "To a Friend Written in a Pocketbook - as a New Year's Gift", 1841 Aug 5 (Box 2, Folder 151)
  - "To a Friend, on His Return to Ceylon as a Missionary, After a Visit in England," and "Better Late than Never", undated (Box 2, Folder 152)
  - "To the Queen, Westminister Abbey on the 28th of June 1838", 1847 Mar 13 (Box 2, Folder 153)
  - [Where Winter spreads a waste of snow...], 1829 Oct 20 (Box 2, Folder 154)
    Verse of nine lines.
  - [With reverence and with godly fear Father of mercies! may we now...], 1836 (Box 2, Folder 155)
- Other Papers, 1824-1920; Series III; 7
  - Invoice to the Rev. J. Hunter from Montgomery, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 156)
    Covering a number of items amounting to £9.2.6. With some notes by the Rev. Hunter on the reverse side.
  - Autograph of Montgomery, clipped, 1826 Nov 25 (Box 2, Folder 157)
  - Printed poems and hymns, 1831-1853 (Box 2, Folder 158)
    General note
    Includes a copy of Hymns for the Opening of Christ Church, Newark on Trent (1837)
  - Engraved portraits of Montgomery, 1825-1887, undated (Box 2, Folder 159)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also folders 45, 50, and 139 for additional portraits of Montgomery.
    Includes a print of the Chapel at the Moravian Settlement at Fulneck.
  - Documents and publications related to Montgomery's death and burial, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 160)
    Includes a copy of The Death of James Montgomery, Esq. with a Sketch of his Life (1854)
  - Articles and clippings about Montgomery and Sheffield, 1824-1920 (Box 2, Folder 161)
  - Miscellaneous notes (not in Montgomery's hand), circa 1913 (Box 2, Folder 162)
- Oversize
  - Aikin, John, of Stoke Newington (in Series I), 1803 Sep 23 (Box 3, Folder 163 Oversize)
  - Aikin, John (in Series I), 1806 Apr 15 (Box 3, Folder 164 Oversize)
  - Aikin, John (in Series I), 1806 Jul 30 (Box 3, Folder 165 Oversize)
  - Aikin, John, of London (in Series I), 1807 Dec 31 (Box 3, Folder 166 Oversize)
  - Aikin, John, of London (in Series I), 1808 Mar 9 (Box 3, Folder 167 Oversize)
  - Aikin, John (in Series I), 1809 Jul 15 (Box 3, Folder 168 Oversize)
  - Aikin, John (in Series I), 1809 Oct 9 (Box 3, Folder 169 Oversize)